four easy steps to assess the
performance of your current inventory
that's what we're going to talk about
this week
[Music]
so this week we are talking about
inventory we don't have enough videos on
inventory on the channel
and this week what i'd like to do is to
share four easy steps to assess how your
inventory is performing and where some
of the gaps are so that you can fix it
now i'll apologize in advance i'm going
to look at some notes why have i got to
look at some notes because one of our
data scientists melanie put this
together for me she's an absolute rocket
scientist and i'm going to have to just
refer to these notes to make sure i get
this right so we're going to put some
charts up on the screen and i'm going to
explain all about it so step one in
assessing your current inventory
performance
is looking at product availability of
course
now i'm sure you're familiar with this
the a b c and d categories
you need to be sure that your a class
items your
your highest demand items highest in
demand have the highest availability
on the example here we're looking at 99
which is really good our b's are at 99
and our c is at 96 percent obviously you
don't want to be running out of the a's
and b's you're just going to really
cheese off your customers so that's the
first very basic step
then we're going to start looking at our
segmentation of the inventory and again
let's use that abc classification
and typically when we're classifying
inventory like that
the a items are those that represent 80
percent of the sales the bs are the next
15 percent of sales and the c's the
final five percent of sales and on this
chart we're looking at how many items
how many skus stop keeping units do we
have in each of those
and we can see that 14
of
our items actually make up 80 of the
sales that's not uncommon and then we've
got 23 making out 15 of the sales that's
fairly fairly common so but it's really
important that you understand that
okay what about excess and obsolete
stock oh so many businesses have loads
of that really important thing to check
your inventory health so we can see on
this chart there isn't too much excess
which is good
and really not any dead stock so dead
stock is stock that hasn't moved in at
least 12 months
excess stock generally we would classify
as having more than six months of stock
so that's not too bad and then what
we're looking at is aging stock by cost
of goods so we're looking at the value
of it the cost of goods
so zero to three months we've got lots
of stock in there a bs and cs that's
where you would expect to see most of
the inventory investment and then it
tiles off fairly quickly on this chart
though we're seeing this quite a lot
over six months six to 12 months 12 to
24 so that would be something that i
would definitely be investigating in
this example so that's step one having a
quick look at the inventory health
step two then is understanding
our inventory right down to a skew level
and making a plan for every single skew
stock keeping unit
so this is an interesting chart that
we're looking at here what we're looking
at here is the count
of
the frequency of demand of stock by the
abc classification and the value in
terms of cogs cost of goods sold
so very simply if it's an aaa and we've
got 182 items in there these are the
high value
fast moving high demand products and
then it will be the the bbs and so on so
that's a really good way to have a look
at your inventory what this allows you
to do of course is to target service
levels to the individual types of
inventory you know managing your safety
stock stocking strategies it helps you
with your forecasting and replenishment
and you need to understand it to this
level of course so you can write an
inventory policy so thank you for that
one melanie that's really cool and then
step three
kpis ah we talk about kpis a lot on the
channel um make sure that you link your
kpis to your overall supply chain
strategy and don't go overboard on kpis
so here are some that we would suggest
in terms of inventory product
availability definitely dipot delivery
in full on time everybody knows that one
what about sci-fi supply in full on time
coming in from your suppliers the other
end stock turns obviously very common
one forecast accuracy what's your
forecast accuracy like and gemroy gross
margin return on investment i don't see
a lot of organizations measuring that
that's really looking at the return that
you're getting on that inventory
investment i'm sure we've got a video on
it if not i'll make one
then the next step make sure that you've
got the right sort of software to be
running your inventory to be managing it
now i am not here to promote any
particular software product i go out of
my way to be totally unbiased
all i will say
is that make sure that whatever software
you're picking meets your functional
needs so let's flash up some of the
things that you might want you might
want to have alerts when you're getting
to sort of low stock levels you might
want to have the ability to balance
stock levels in different locations you
certainly want forecasting and inventory
planning
you certainly want container
optimization a lot of businesses
things like auto scheduling echelon
inventory so at different stages through
your supply chain being able to see
what's being held
network optimization all kinds of
reporting so you need to understand what
you need in terms of functionality for
your inventory management software and
and then you know get out there and have
a look
it's always difficult when people say
what's what's some good inventory
management software um i mean we very
often help our consulting clients
through this process to select software
um we certainly have no bias on any
particular one
but it's interesting that they can range
from
as little as 20 to 30 000 for quite a
good inventory management software
package up to millions
so
it's important that you pick the right
one
so there we go here are melanie's four
steps to really getting a handle on your
inventory and understanding your
inventory health you know assess your
inventory health to begin with make that
plan around every single stock keeping
unit review your kpis and then if you're
still doing things on spreadsheets you
probably want to look at some specialist
software to manage your inventory as
well so there we go some tips on
inventory from our guru melanie
thanks for watching this week if you've
got any questions or any of that do
comment down below if you're not
subscribed to the channel do think of
subscribing and we'll see you next week
bye for now
[Music]
you